as simple as someone mentioned it is a
real shame the we encounter technical
issues when we're having an event of
such a on such a vital topic and really
hope and I'm in fact I don't need to
hope because I'm convinced of it that
they the content of the event will make
up for that for the loss of time here's
what we're going to do first things
first we are going to we're recording
the event everything will be sent tight
afterwards we have a Facebook live
streaming link that is being sent to
everybody
and it will the whole event will be
streamed live on Facebook those of you
who are with us you know hopefully
you'll be able to stay with us if you
need to leave at any point obviously you
will get the recording and you can and
you can come back in just people that
you know who can't get in you know send
them the bass because I think we've just
put it in the chat box what we're going
to do we're going to run I'm at a
session till 10:20 then we're going to
have Jason and Paul there and we're
going to run into the break a little bit
only to the extent that they're actually
able to stay with us because I don't
want to take up their time if they've
got other commitments but we'll we'll
try and pocket or than as best we can
and gain back the time in the schedule
break
this event is a by acknowledging that
none of us have done enough on tackling
racism across higher education and
coming away with a plan of action to do
more and if everyone who expressed
interest in this affair attended did did
just one thing in their institution or
any or in their particular context the
the scale of change would be absolutely
enormous so we really really hope that
what you will come away with is a kind
of things that things that you can do to
make make a real difference wherever you
are a few very quick housekeeping notes
feel free to post to the chat box but do
be aware because it's quite well
attended we won't necessarily be able to
pick up questions that way so if you
want to ask a question please use the
Q&A box
feel free to up great questions if you
if you brought them more answer than
others so that we can kind of pick up
the ones that are most popular and the
wonky team is in the chat so do if you
have any issues do direct a message to
them that's me
mark Jim and DK and I only remains for
me to introduce I must say allottees
known to many of you as a
former vice president of higher
education and yes and for his national
advocacy for universities to take action
and closing the bam attainment gap which
has culminated in the influential
closing the gap report with Universities
UK he's my consultant with a nice group
and he's given up his personal time to
co-produce and host this event and for
which we're incredibly grateful do
continue by the way to keep posting your
resources in the chat books and I am
collecting them and I will I will share
those afterwards i'ma take them to open
the event with his own insight on what a
whole University approach to racism
tackling racism might look like so thank
you very much I'm attained over to you
thank you Debbie and cooking everybody
can see my screen this is a very timely
and important event and I'm really
pleased that so many of you are joining
us today as I said we're gonna have to
move some of the timings around we're
looking forward to a really engaging
conversation this morning just a brief
introduction to myself as they be said I
would say I'm a consultant and now screw
on the right you can see a bit of work
that last Toastmasters on Australian
consulting firm with over 20 years of
experience in higher education and in
the time that I've been at now a number
of universities on the whole range of
projects but before that I was vice
president of higher education at the
National Union of Students and in that
role --roll co-chaired the NUS UK
closing the gap report which looked into
tackling the BMI attainment gap so lots
of really interesting stuff there and
love that informs my talk today you've
got my email address if you do want to
get in in touch and also might return
between tweeting memes I occasionally
have something interesting to say about
higher education policy so please do
give that a follower and obviously do
you engage in the conversation today um
so let's just kick things off as I said
this is a timely discussion a timely
conversation the murder of George Floyd
in America sent shockwaves around the
world and have sparked lots of
conversations and
lots of institutions and organizations
and governments have taken various forms
of actions on a personal note there is
something trying to find the right word
in the sense despairing about the fact
that it you know it takes a black person
to die before these events are these
issues are surfaced in this way but I
think we shouldn't miss this chance
really to look at all the ways in which
black lives are discriminated against
and structurally disadvantaged across
the West and ask ourselves these real
searching questions about what we can do
to change and this is a conversation for
many sexes is a conversation today for
higher education and I'm glad that so
many people have turned out for this
conversation
so as Debbie said what we'll cover today
and I'll kick off by very whizzing
through some high-level thoughts about
the importance of taking a whole
institution approach to tackling racism
I'll then hand over to some fantastic
speakers that we have today and look at
some some of the three other areas we'll
be looking at studying and working in
academic communities we looking at
intersections capturing and acting on
lived experience and then we'll be
looking at leadership there will be a
short break between two and three and as
we've said before please do join us on
the conversation on twitter hashtag
blacklivesmatter
aichi and let's keep the conversation
going not just for this morning but
beyond as well so I'm just going to kick
things off by saying talking about the
importance of taking a whole institution
approach to tackling racism and why
that's so important
the first thing is to say it's a start
off in a slightly provocative space and
is to say that universities have played
a role a critical role in the creation
of race as a concept I think sometimes
there's a tendency for us to look at the
university sector like other sexes and
say look there's racism that exists in
wider society and you
versity are not immune to that so we
need to do something to address that but
sometimes that doesn't quite acknowledge
the the nuance which is that actually
universities were involved in the
creation of race as a concept it
produced academics and thinkers who
created lots of these racial hierarchies
which in turn provided intellectual
underpinnings for colonialism and
slavery and on the rise that of this of
the PowerPoint you can see at the top an
academic called blumenbach sketching out
five different skulls which which you
know to be obviously fictitious today
but five different skulls that were to
signify five different races and we've
got Immanuel Kant again revered is one
of the founding fathers in philosophy
but he too in 1775 I think it was in a
piece called the different races of man
also aspired lots of set out different
races and said why they were different
and ordered them in a certain hierarchy
so it's really really important that not
only are there issues to do with race
and to do the racial equality of higher
education the sexes
unfortunately played a role in their
creation and but the other thing to say
is I'm sure many of you are at
institutions where you would say that
your assertion wasn't around at that
time and that's that's a valid point but
it's important to understand that the
sector today came out of that ecosystem
they were all part of the same ecosystem
there lots of legacies that continue
today which I'll touch on briefly so
what are these like
uncover courts will speak at quite a few
of these in our conversation today but
there's a 26% attainment gap between
between white students and black
students in terms of outcomes we know
there lots of black students have a lack
of sense of belonging in their
institution which is a real issue in
concern racial harassment reporting
structures are inadequate we've got
lower continuation rates for black
students as well the curriculum big
focus of many of these campaigns is
you're eccentric and doesn't reflect the
diversity of the student experience we
have very few black professors in either
fewer even fewer and black women
professors whew and that translates a
few black singer leaders and we know
that then the progression as part of
that the progression to postgraduate
research is very poor for black students
as well so there's a lot of work to be
done and racial inequalities as we know
still persist what is a vision for
ending racial inequality put a question
mark because I think it's an open-ended
question I think there's lots of people
have will have different views and
different opinions on what that looks
like the important things to say is up
but I put a photo on the rights of some
smiling black students the reality is it
is more than just having some smiley
faces on your prospectus or on your
website it's about real fundamental
change in outcomes so things like
supporting support services are
culturally competent the curriculum is
reflective of the diverse student
background you have a diverse academic
and non-academic staff at all levels so
right through the university instances
of racism are dealt with very very
quickly but they're rare black students
crucially feel like they belong and as
possible the attainment gaps or any
other disparities are eliminated as well
so that that is part of where we're
trying to head to and I'm sure many
people and we'll have other things to
add to that list so where are we now
well as this conversation shows debates
about racism and colonialism are alive
and well we do have sector wide
initiatives which are in place so you
see there the race
Charter mark and the office of students
as well has regulated as part of the
access and participation plans for
institutions to report against closing a
lot of these gaps sector leaders are
taking issue more seriously undoubtedly
and that's a change that we've seen in
the last couple of years I mentioned and
the NUS Universities UK black attainment
gap report and that was part of the
sector I think really taking this issue
more seriously but but but but I think
there was a lack of what I would call a
comprehensive institution wide approach
to tackling racial inequalities and I'd
be very keen to hear from from you on
Twitter on the chat if your institution
has taken this approach and I will go
into what that looks like in the next
couple of minutes so different
institutional approaches now I'm
conscious a lot on the screen so I'm not
asking you to absorb all of this right
now
but I thought I'd just give two
illustrative examples of what this could
look like so on the Left we have County
sure University of course and made up
University and I'll briefly describe to
you what they didn't then we'll move on
to the other fictitious University of
the University of Justice so country
University what do they do the
university executive team launches a
Bayman a quality strategy one month
after the black lives matter that
strategy is responsibility of the e nd
team delivery is met within existing
budgets attainment gap work remains with
the PVC education and in the first year
we get rollout of unconscious bias
training not mandatory but encouraged
three new groups with black
representation to tackle racism and
attainment gut committee student
experience and staff recruitment working
group all black students are enrolled on
a mentoring scheme as soon as they
arrive to raise their aspirations and
black staff and students invited to
listening sessions every month to give
their views on how to tackle racism in
the university so senior leadership are
clearly behind it lots and lots of
activity and lots of initiatives let's
compare that with the University of fib
Chester on the right for what do they do
well the University of just to take a
slightly different approach the
executive team engages with external
specialists and the Students Union to
conduct an institution-wide consultation
of
staff and students on race and that
report disaggregates experiences of the
BMI category provides very clear
recommendations for outcomes and actions
and those actions are prioritized by the
staff and students who were consulted
the executive team then recruits at PVCC
inclusion who reports at the VC sits on
the exec team oversees the
implementation and recommendations and
crucially brings together all the EMD
work in the institution and then the
exact same launch a 200k anti-racism
strategy that includes mandatory race
equity training for all staff race
equity training incorporated into
inductions a culture change program
which is institution wide to upskill all
staff on inclusive practices in teaching
and in the workplace and then a racial
harassment reporting unit is established
to deal with all forms of racism
experienced by staff and students now
I'm sure many of you have guessed which
one I think is the better one crucially
though even though the University of
Chester is in my view the better
approach it isn't the right approach it
there is no right approach
it's the actions and the outcomes and
the solutions will all be institution
specific and that's very very important
but I'll just briefly talk to you why I
think that the one on the right is a
better approach than the countess
University on the left
just very quickly country university you
can see that there is clearly buy-in
from the senior team they want to do
something about it but they launched it
very quickly and I in that that there
might be concerned about the extent to
which there was extensive consultation
we've got the alarm bells about the
delivery met within existing budgets and
I'll talk about the importance of
visuals and this stuff later we've got a
bit of division between where some of
this work sit so is it with the PDC
education is it with the India team
that's clearly in what I've sketched out
not really a sight where this is being
brought together and that could create
some confusion we then got the rollout
of unconscious bias training which is
non mandatory I think I'm conscious bias
training in my view is outdated and you
need a bit more of a comprehensive
equity training program which is far
more on the education side rather than
sort of the online unconscious bias
training that you get and the fact this
not mandatory means that people who are
interested so some people on this call
will be going but what about those
people who perhaps need it more and he
want and they're solely interested real
concerns about the proliferation of
committees with black representation if
it's typical of any institution in the
UK and the number of black staff will be
few and far between so forcing them to
spread themselves thinly on lots and
lots of different committees is a real
concern and we've seen it happen in lots
of institutions we've got this idea that
all black students should be enrolled in
a mentoring scheme immediately that
seems like a solution has been found
before drilling into whether that's the
issue
lots of black sea's and some very high
aspirations but there are structural
challenges and barriers there and then
we've got this idea of listening
sessions again something that feels good
but is it useful is it what's been asked
for there are questions there moving on
to fib Chester what are the positives
here well clearly there's been extensive
concert of consultative process and it
should be a process that has the trust
of the communities who are affected
we've got that important aspect on that
second point there on decide location BM
II and understanding that it isn't the
case that all people in that category
have the same experiences and it's
important to make sure the
recommendations are prioritized and
effect that we've then got the of a
senior leader who is to spearhead this
work report directly to the VC that's
something which we've seen very
effective in lots of different
institutions and really does bring
together all that really important work
and then we've got the launching of a
new strategy with significant resource
and 200 K I'm sure if there any senior
leaders on the call probably bulk that
figure but the reality is institutions
spend that amount of money and a lot lot
more when doing institution wide and big
transformation projects and this needs
to be seen as part of that so I'm not
saying that's the figure but getting
interest
where we're thinking okay how are we
actually going to resource this I think
is very important we've got the
mandatory race equity training so not
just unconscious bias training but as an
institution a-fib Chester said well we
want to take the seriously we want to
see this as cool as our training for all
staff so as other things are mandatory
we put basically training as part of
that it's incorporated into induction as
well which is also very important that
all students coming in I have a chance
to explore these issues as well and then
that's part of an institution and wired
culture change program and that's to
upskill all staff and inclusive
practices you notice on the left that
decolonizing the curriculum is there but
is it core is it part of a wider program
and so that you don't have to sort of be
teaching this stuff in a piecemeal way
it's actually part of the way in which
we do things at the University and then
that final point about race racial
harassment reporting unit established
again showing that centrality of the
coordinated approach there so as I said
the University of Chester is by no means
the correct answer but I think it speaks
to an approach which is a bit more
centrally coordinated it has the
resource behind it and will be more
effective in the long run so just to
kind of recap on that what are the key
principles when tackling racial
inequalities in our education you've got
to take an institution-wide coordinated
approach that means senior leaders need
to be coordinating that essentially
you've got a center black students and
staff experiences when implementing
solutions but when doing so they
shouldn't be the ones who are carrying
out the solutions or implementing it
themselves without the support as part
of that then source appropriate
expertise I see a lot of here a lot of
very well-meaning individuals and
institutions kind of twiddling their
thumbs saying we don't really know what
to do we don't know what to do if it's
in any other instance where you don't
know what to do you go and source the
expertise and we need to start seeing
that as that far too often lots of these
issues are treated as a sort of
political issue that sort of needs to be
managed politically as opposed to a
capability issue or a lack of capability
issue so if you have if you don't have
those capabilities you need to get
actual recruitment you need to find the
people that do and then crucially when
those people are in place you then need
to resource that
and if that involves a a big culture
change program that needs to be part of
that braces already find a quick point
on that resourcing point actually as I
said this isn't an add-on this needs to
be a core of what the university does
and I think crucially if you do this
properly you will find that a lot of the
processes and other procedures and other
systems that you haven't to change to
ensure that black students and the black
staff are not being discriminated
against you will find lots of issues
that need to be solved which will
benefit all staff and all students as
well so this isn't something that is
some sort of special case just for black
students or black stuff if you can so
black students and they say yeah
actually a massive problem is the
timetabling and that's really negatively
affecting our our student experience
well that's something that I'm sure lots
of students all students will be
affected by but probably not as acutely
we fix that problem you fixed it for the
widest student population as well so in
terms of making the eye open for that
resource you've got to take in a
holistic way and then just sort of some
very brief sector-wide recommendations
which we come at which we can unpack on
just to get people thinking I've asked
us because today to really get ourselves
into solutions focused area I think
there are some things missing from the
sector which we could benefit from so I
think we could do with a BMI graduate
schemes for progression into University
professional services you know we like
to focus a lot on the education side
sometimes we missed the importance of
diversifying University professional
services who are critical to the running
of our universities and make decisions
every minute that will affect students
and all students so it's really
important that those are diverse on the
academic side we do need a sex-wise
Graduate scheme campaign for progression
into PDR and that includes contextual
offers if we acknowledge that there's an
attainment gap what are we doing to
acknowledge the fact that and those
students may not have the grades that
typically may lend themselves to a PDR
reach so and I know that there are
organizations out there which are
focused on this area I think that needs
a bit more resourcing I'd like to see
some accredited a tree race equity CPD
programs tailored to university world if
they are there please do tweet me please
let me know let's say these resources
but I think you know if I'm working the
finance division what does race equity
look like can I do a course that way
makes it much easier for universities if
they want to identify those individuals
who are taking this seriously to make
sure those individuals are are
identified by having these CPD programs
as you would with any other capabilities
as well and then the final point I think
is in the next frontier
I think there's a lot of conversation
about this within the sector we need to
engage the professional statutory and
regulatory bodies as well because they
often have a big say on what's in the
curriculum and the way in which our
education is providing that also
included those organizations that take
students on for placements and obviously
employers as well so how do we make sure
that the entire h ee co system and the
wider players as well are also included
in the conversation so that's a sort of
whistle stock talk through some of my
thoughts on why I think an
institution-wide
approach is necessary for higher
education I won't take questions right
now I think we will move swiftly on to
our first our first panel discussion
today Debbie is there anything just want
to very quick clarifications at this
point
one is is that are you willing to make
your slides available because everyone's
desperate to know will they get them
afterwards okay so everyone be assured
that's going to happen and the other
thing I think is probably worth
addressing at this point is the kind of
people are questioning what are we
talking about are we talking about black
are we talking about babe what you know
what what are the categories we're
dealing with here and I think that's
kind of worth articulating at this point
how are you thinking about that so and
that's it that's a very very good prompt
M something I should have adjust right
at the beginning look the same category
is is quite controversial at times
because we know it doesn't capture the
nuances of the different experience I
think it is useful in one sense because
it there are clear disparities there so
we can't look at by category bayman and
all the individuals who are within
and obey me and see that there are
disparities there I think in if the the
movement at the moment has demonstrated
one thing is that black students the
black individuals on the whole are at
the bottom of the pile they are the most
acutely affected by all these issues and
it's important to I think focus on those
experiences and more keep me at this
time but also in general um racial
inequalities exist within society we
should be seeking to tackle all of them
but disaggregating those experiences is
absolutely vital as well and that means
in this context you are consulting those
different communities finding those
distinct concerns and making sure that
when you're taking action and that is
front of mind so by no means lump vme
and bam all together but understand that
you know Asian students will face
discrimination students from other
background non-white um backgrounds will
face discriminations as well what are we
doing for all those groups but not
missing of course and black students
black staff who are often at the sharp
end of that
brilliant thank you so I will move us on
to our first panel today I'm really
excited to have some fantastic speakers
lined up for you today firstly we're
going to talk briefly about studying and
working in academic communities are
confronting bias and Prejudice thinking
about those cultures talking about those
microaggressions and biases and how to
recognize them if perhaps you're not
from those communities and explore some
of those areas where bias may be lurking
and joining me is dr. Jason are they who
is the assistant professor in sociology
at Durham University in the Department
of Sociology he is a visiting research
fellow at the Ohio State University in
the office of diversity and inclusion a
research associate at Nelson Mandela
University in the Center for critical
studies in higher education
transformation and a trustee of the
running me trust the UK's leading race
equality think-tank Jason is also a
fellow of the Royal Society of the Arts
and a trustee of the British
sociological Association and sits on the
Centre for labour and social studies the
national advisory panel for that and is
a school governor at Shastri Park
Primary School in London Jason thank you
for joining us and and also Paulette
Williams who's the head of student
success projects and co-lead for the
Bahm awarding projects at the University
College London UCL which the three-year
project which aims to eliminate the bane
attainment gap and Paula has worth UCL
since 2005 primarily in widening
participation and access and is also
involved in a lot of work in terms of
progression to postgraduate study as
well which I'm sure she she can talk
about later say Jason
Paulette thank you so much for for
joining us Jason perhaps if we start
with you just very quickly in terms of
how this will work with these sessions
speakers will speak for about five
minutes and then we'll I'll kick off
with a few questions and then we'll open
it to the floor I think Debbie will help
us coordinate some of these questions
that are coming through so Jason if we
start with you firstly thank you so much
for having me here
really really appreciated
interesting time one of the better term
it's always a privilege to share any
platform with the fantastic quality ins
so I think one of the most important
things is as kind of a Mateus already
alluded to we've reached a really
seminal moment you know in kind of race
equality history almost I think that is
quite an interesting juncture for us to
really kind of reevaluate the
instruments were using think about some
of the complacency I set in across the
sector and maybe think about what the
sector actually represents so if we kind
of begin with this idea of university
being a microcosm of society and you
know this kind of Canon the whole
thing's egalitarian you know inclusive I
think interestingly as one of society's
major institutions a lot of that is
actually quite contradictory so
universities in many ways are actually
worse than other and to some other
institutions in terms of race equality
and having penetrative interventions
that really tackle and address all of
racism in its kind of systemic cultural
and insidious forms
I suppose one of the things that's kind
of really important is thinking about
the cultures that enable this prejudice
and I think one of the things that
becomes interesting is how complicit we
can all be in those cultures so in for
example when we kind of think about the
question of bane staff particularly
professional staff and academics for
what we see continuously our games are
being overlooked for promotion being
looked over looked for opportunities to
progress being overlooked in terms of
pay differentials and what becomes
interesting is that as colleagues when I
talk about that complicity are these
things that we aware of how much of a
blind eye do we turn to these situations
and I suppose when we kind of think
about what we're kind of I guess
reconceptualizing in light of what's
happened over the last month or so what
a lie ship looks like that giving up a
privilege actually a huge part of
acknowledging it is actually recognizing
that there are differentials in the
first place which don't reside in a
meritocracy
so I think there's this idea that you
know I've earned
I've got to there's never a
disqualification of that but so have
bein individuals and they are not
regulated basically or reputationally in
the same ways I think in terms of the
patterns of prejudice I think one of the
things that's really interesting is
thinking about a subtleness of racism
within higher education institutions and
authority more generally and I think
interestingly what we are now seeing is
I think if racism was a race I think
there's always this idea that we can
keep abreast of it or keep ahead of it
and I think that's quite difficult
because it's starting from a pretty
strong position in the first place and
one of the things I can't urge us to
really think about is really one of the
cultures that I guess sustained is
purchased but more importantly the
patterns so the contours of racism are
actually quite hard to track but how we
can stay abreast of it as i'm mateus
kind of alluded to earlier is really
this collective action I think the
collective action becomes really really
important so interestingly we always
kind of left people of color
bein black whichever inference you
prefer to use to deal with issues of
racism even though in many cases they
don't have the power or the privilege to
absolve themselves from that situation
or in many cases they never as I've
never met a person of color that asked
to be in a racist situation so the
actual construct of racism is you know
has kind of its roots and its tentacles
really stem from white supremacy and
ideas around white privilege so I do
think it's important that we think about
how we
culturally address and dismantle those
aspects because I guess some of the
mechanisms that we've been using haven't
worked and I will suggest they may have
not worked because there has been an
onus on black people to figure out
issues around racism and really again
the emphasis really is on that
collective action and white people
really kind of stepping up to the plate
and thinking about how they can
reconstruct rise and redefine their
ownership with this notion of racism
continuously reinventing itself I think
that's really really important
particularly in spaces of leadership in
spaces of privilege in spaces of
decision
making that kind of stakeholder elijah
becomes really really important and
integral to what we are looking to do in
terms of having a having an inclusive
academy that is reflective of the
multicultural society that we live in
lastly I only want to talk about
microaggressions and the biases that
kind of encompass this when you're not
the target so I think one of the
interesting things is from a personal
perspective I've always been in
situations where when people kind of get
assemblance that there's something
that's happened that's slightly on
toward one of the interesting things is
really this idea of Jason I think
something happened there but I don't you
know are you alright are you okay and I
always kind of felt inside you know I
prefer you know I know what happened or
I prefer that Elijah is actually
converted into challenging the person
who may have inflicted that particular
laceration at the time and it is that
interesting thing with microaggressions
you know its cumulative its death by a
thousand cuts in terms of hemorrhaging
in terms of kind of I guess stopping
that hemorrhaging or bleeding almost
that emotional bleeding what we do need
to see is people not being complicit in
that by challenging it you know very
often frame academics and freshmen staff
are in vulnerable positions and the
challenging of that is consequential on
already you know damage pipelines in
terms of career progression and actually
engagement within the wider University
so I do think it's kind of really
important when we kind of see those acts
of microaggressions which are subtle
acts of racism they're not over they're
not over acts of racism and interesting
I think we all gravitate to all those
overt acts erase them it's actually a
subtle acts there are more Penniston and
more dangerous over a period of time for
the banging member of staff and I'll
just conclude by saying in terms of the
particular areas of unexamined bias I
think one of the things that becomes
really pertinent it's really thinking
about the privilege that we all hold so
I always try and work from positionality
perspective and I recognize that as a
black male I occupy a very privileged
position particularly over black women
and women of color
and I recognize that the unexamined
biased in this kind of work has read
labor that happens in terms of race to
quality work and it's I think it'd be
remiss of me not to say that that labor
has been taken up by predominantly black
women and South Asian women the Academy
and again often unenumerated you know
fiscally and reputationally do you think
that if anything else this is a call for
all of us to engage in a collective
endeavor which challenges unexamined
biases while we lean to paying women to
kind of resolve us or take us out this
problem and really think about how we
can make this a more collective endeavor
and again just thank you so much to
everyone that's tuned in today it really
really means a lot and I feel very
fortunate to again be showing this
platform to fantastic Paula Williams and
thank you having me here thank you
Nathan thanks so much there's a lot
you've covered there and a lot and so
we'll unpack in the next bit but first
um Paulette bigots hear from you yeah
sure thanks I would say and also it's
great to be here with Jason as well so I
wanted to kind of start off by saying
that you've already touched on this the
title of this event was black as well
and the description spoke a lot about
pain and I grieve you I will say
sometimes you know that label can be
used it can be effective but it can also
be abused and become extremely
ineffective and I just kind of wanted to
touch on the fact that we've seen it
being used definitely living
institutions in my role at UCL where you
know it helps to get buy-in for certain
things and it helps to secure resources
we've seen it being ineffective because
you know even within that if you're
trying to address the issues faced by
black students who report by your NSS
that they're the least satisfied in your
institutions
you're not going to address that in the
same way that you would for and possibly
you know a project we've got you co
Muslim women who are going out on
placements as part of their course it's
two completely different things so when
you bunch them all together
it causes problems and it also causes
problems in terms of data and the way
that we analyze data so we've seen some
headlines maybe where it's been abused
in terms of recruitment numbers when
institutions talk about the number of
brain students that they've recruited
always kind of trying to overshadow the
fact that the numbers of recruitment the
current numbers for black students are
still extremely low particularly sort of
Russell group and any institution so I
just wanted to make that point to sort
of start off with so I was asked just to
kind of talk about my position in terms
of these issues it wasn't mentioned they
didn't mention it but I'm also founder
of an organization called leading roots
and we support black students form sort
of perspective students in going into
undergraduate all the way through to
those that are kind of thinking about
doing a PhD and we've already heard
about the challenges that they face
along that sort of pipeline from the
start when they're just thinking about
it to become an academics so for me you
know I thought about this moment we keep
talking about this moment in terms of
black lives my cell and it kind of
dawned on me that this moment is
different to everyone right so it means
something different to black people to
white people and to higher education
more generally I think for black people
and I can only really speak for myself
and maybe some of the people in my
circle that I speak to you know my
blackness preys on every aspect of my
life right from you know entertainment
food motherhood whatever and I loved
that you know my blackness is not a
disadvantage for me the issue comes when
you know I encounter racism which
threatens basically to overshadow so
much during my life and that is
reflected as well in the workplace and
in higher education through the
education system so I know maybe it's
been framed at the moment as like a
negative thing but it's not for me
I am kind of I think it's important to
kind of emphasize that this is an all
negative and the issue is racism so I
think for a lot of white people and of
course there are many white people who
have been doing this work who in this
moment are trying to sort of leverage
opportunities for black people and black
light initiatives
I'm fortunate enough to account
encounter many of them through leading
boots work for UCI work but you know and
many of them are sort of kind of
acknowledging that a lot of black people
as Jason touched on leading this work
and we're tired and they're removing
some of that labor for us which is
amazing but for many white people I
think this moment comes with a lot of
enthusiasm and a desire to sort of learn
more and a lot of black people that I've
spoken to you we're not really saw we
don't understand why now I'd love to
hear in the comments maybe from some
people who can just tell me why not why
what has kind of made you so much more
open and willing to hear us I think it's
an amazing thing but if we don't kind of
understand why that is we don't really
understand or we can't really predict
how long it will last
right so a lot of us are confused we're
a bit skeptical and again we're a bit
tired but this moment is not about
charity work right
what I hope is gained for me is that
individuals and institutions take
forward any learning from this time in
our day to day interactions with our
students with our staff and just
everyday right so I think it's important
to make sure that whatever it is that
you're learning or the way that you're
learning or or trying to channel this
enthusiasm is done with a bit of depth
you
so you maybe you've read a book or
you've gone to a protest I see loads of
kind of resources in the chat which are
great there's a process between that and
then you know heading up initiatives in
an institution or you know kind of
people that have gone got in contact
with me which is amazing that want to
start work but there's a bit in the
middle if you haven't done that which
requires you to digest how you fit
within this right and how you've played
a part how we've all played a part in
what's happening so I think this moment
for higher education is about
transparency is about authenticity and
it's about it's about honesty right so I
think HDI's should have fairly low
expectations in terms of the expected
response from black people and people of
color more generally if you have
students within your institution and
staff living an institution which you
probably have who have experienced
racial harassment as a meze touched on
your institution is kind of the
history's rooted in racism and if you
know those incidents of racism haven't
been addressed where often the system
has failed black people in terms of you
know when we're trying to report
incidents that have happened there are
people within your institution who are
really seen as some untouchable because
of the power that they have within your
institution and whether that's to do
with status or whether that's to do with
you know the amount of funding that
they're bringing in when you tweet black
lives matter and you release this
statement despite all the amazing work
that is going on and I've witnessed that
from many of my colleagues at UCL people
will not believe you
and unfortunately they've been let down
by you and it will take time to build up
that trust so you know I would hope that
institutions keep plugging away keep
putting that the resources into that
work and you know show the stamina and
that we've had to for many generations
until one day that balance shifts and
you know you've done enough to kind of
show the results and make a change
within the sector so this work is
definitely ongoing and I would say I
think I'm saying you also had a kind of
article on this I used to kind of say oh
it's going to take a long time I still
believe it will take a long time but I
think part of that is in terms of like
the investment of time so it's not like
a surface thing that I will take showed
with the two separate universities an
investment of time quality time but you
know Cove in 19 has showed us how
quickly we can move on things you know
all those sort of barriers in terms of
committees and structures and all these
things that we have to do in order to
get things moving I don't know those are
because clearly when something is urgent
it can be addressed quickly and I think
there needs to be more urgency placed on
on on this issue right so for me I hope
this moment is a time for change in
terms of our perspective but also in
terms of the way that we address issues
that are facing so many people within
institutions and affecting our it's not
just our day-to-day life at work but
then that carries on into our life in
general and can have a really really bad
effect so I'll leave it there just
looking forward to the discussion with
you guys thanks Paula and you very some
really really important issues as well
following fulling Jason I think that
that point about the trust regaining the
trust and beyond statements I think it
is really important and I can imagine
that University calm scenes for very
keen to get out I close my statements
the first time I've really seen
universities in it as a whole kind of
talk about some of these issues in this
sort of in this sort of way I had a
moment like this but I can imagine you
would ask somebody in the university
comms team what
the reaction was like in the comments or
being quote tweeted and I I saw lots of
things our numbers of students talking
really genuinely about their experiences
and the challenges that they'd had was
they've been there whilst they're there
or or years and years ago and that
really should highlight the importance
of you know it's not about just
statements it's about real and
structural change and just both of you
really quickly just to kick off we've
got we've got about 15 minutes for some
questions and I'll ask let me to see
what's coming through I suppose I'd came
to know you both touched on the
importance of white colleagues either
intervening in certain situations or
actually taking the initiative and doing
some of the work and some of the labor
in this space do you have any examples
of where you've seen that being done
effectively and and I suppose if not
what sorts of things would you kind of
be looking for for your white colleagues
to sort of really be doing in this space
and perhaps we stopped adjacent I
suppose and I myself an idealist so I
always trying to clear best in every one
way possible and I guess where I have
seen some fantastic examples or I guess
why I had a ship if this is what we're
talking about and it has been in terms
of people disrupting privileged spaces
and in particular really looking for
ways to challenge differentials and
instances so I'm really I'm very
fortunate to work with Professor Mickey
Bolivar is a press of sociology at
Durham University and over the last six
years a lot of her work has really been
around challenging whiteness and lits I
guess it's tentacles in terms of what it
infiltrates and how it infiltrates too
and a lot of our works really been
focused around thinking about Bain
differentials particularly in terms of
you can in terms of you class and
getting into particular types of
universities and really promoting an
agenda at Durham to really challenge and
look at the star of copulation and how
we can diversify that star population
and she's also kind of actively engaged
in looking to support Bain
PR students in terms of making
transitions into higher education and I
spiked Nikki's fantastic example because
of the work she's done over a sustained
period so without being cynical you know
she was engaging this before it's kind
of become fashionable you know she's
been as long as I've known her which is
nearly six years she's been doing this
work and another colleague that I'd like
to point to is dr. Zuri sorry dr. dena
Zoe Bellary Jie Queen's University
Belfast there's also been a fantastic
wine really tries to kind of shine a
light on I guess global inequality
within the Academy but in particular how
what people kind of take spaces and are
gatekeepers to knowledge and kind of
residents of space without making that
space inclusive and she has engaged in a
lot of challenging work to really
dismantle those spaces and to open up
more spaces for pain professional staff
Thank You Paulette any any examples I
think the best example is probably the
support that I have had for colleagues
specifically in the access and work and
participation team at UCL who supported
leading routes from the very start from
the very sort of for me just having an
idea I think the position that I
envisioned for leading routes is more of
a community LED backlight approach to
addressing some of the issues faced by
black students in higher education and
you know I think we are able to do
things that an institution can't do and
having colleagues that kind of
understand that and I'm not only willing
to support that verbally or you know by
attending events but to help in terms of
funding I think has been extremely
important so I think there are
gatekeepers and if your gatekeeper and
you have that power and privilege to
make decisions I think making those
decisions in a way that you trust people
and you're you're willing to take risks
on people and your will
to do things that other institutions are
not doing I think can pay off for you in
the end
we've helped so many young people
through leading reads and so many
students really do movies we've given a
platform to so many black academics and
that wouldn't have been possible without
some of the allies that we work with at
UCL but also other organizations that we
work with that sort of Wellcome Trust
Sage people who have power that are able
to kind of I guess be distributed in a
way and trust black people and people of
color that we know what is best for our
community in that sense I think that's
really important and I mean you know in
a practical sense there just aren't
enough black people in our education at
the moment to - this will hook on on
such a huge scale so that you know it's
not gonna be done that way and it's the
only shouldn't always be I'm struck by
the number of people as well students
and academics would go into her
education to do their particular area of
expertise and then find themselves being
advocates do not sign up to a course you
know and and you know I say it like that
but then also thinking about the impact
that that then has on their mental
health from this is like what they begin
to prioritize within that space because
they can't let go I understand that urge
to kind of challenge things especially
if that's your personality type but then
equally you know they pay fees and they
don't pay fees to be activists they're
amazing on people but yes it's not right
yeah that's a very good point Debbie
have you had anything through in terms
of questions on anything yeah we've got
quite a quite broad diversity of
questions here and I think and there is
a quite a lot of sort of I guess concern
and anxiety about what the kind of
balance is in collective action between
I guess working closely with with black
students and staff that I lived
experience and the role of white people
as allies and particularly as leaders
and you know I suppose if you feel
there's more to say on that that might
be something to pick up so it was saying
getting you know the difference in
getting black students involved and
versus kind of expecting them to do all
the work and actually and also a request
for of an example of someone making an
intervention a positive intervention in
a in a kind of decision-making space or
a leadership space that challenge that
moment of of microaggression or
prejudice Jason maybe you mentioned in
and what you're talking about
in terms of on that last point about
there's somebody afterwards coming up to
you and saying are you okay what
happened there you know
is everything okay and and kind of
hoping that an intervention that's kind
of been made beforehand I'm also struck
I'm also but also balancing that against
the sort of point you made about this
stuff is cumulative and and sometimes
even as black staff or black students
you don't really is sometimes very
difficult to pinpoint specific
microaggressions but you realize over
time that that's where you'd be enough
but have you ever seen or if not seen
what could you what would you like to
see in terms of like self intervening in
those spaces I'm sorry why self
intervening in days and I guess for me
it's always been in one of those things
that's been you know it's it's it's not
so much the public humiliation I think
it's the residual effect but often when
you know one goes to lay their head down
at night and they think about what they
may have they reflect upon a day and
they think about what they've
encountered and for me I've always been
struck by you know my general
disposition has always been to if I saw
my brother or sister or anything in
between struggling trying intervene and
I'm trying dude and I often joke about
it but it's definitely cost me three
jobs so I I've done it and I do continue
to do it and sometimes what I just find
interesting is the observation of what
happened afterwards and I suppose as I
said to kind of reiterate what I would
like particularly when we're talking
about you know advocating on behalf of
staff and students as well because I
think it's important to include students
in this there are times where students
have made a complaint range and to make
a complaint about
why member of star may have said
something inappropriate or acted
inappropriately with regards to being
racially discriminatory and often it's
been brushed off and if then you have
other members of staff who say I've
heard that member of staff say that
before but actually you know and that
kind of raising a head above the parapet
you know I personally would like to see
my colleagues you know look to disrupt
those spaces more you know be exact I
think as it also as a as a bein person
when you're in that space and you
challenge that you are kind of
categorized as aggressive you know angry
you know sometimes inarticulate you know
lacking restraint where I think when
white people occupy those spaces there
seems forthright confident assertive and
it's kind of thinking about one how we
re conceptualize and redefine the
language the physical language of that
space the physical literacy even of that
space and to just think about really
when what people observe those things
the complicity in that act of
microaggression is to actually be silent
it's not challenges to not say anything
and I think it's kind of without being
harsh quite useless afterwards to point
out to the individual who's encountered
that particular form of who you know
systemic violence you know I understand
what you're going for him so story you
went through it you know that that kind
of you know horse after the bolt has
bolted tight kind of discourse is kind
of it doesn't really help and it
deftly doesn't help staff and Effie
doesn't help students and I've seen
students encounter pain over a sustained
period where there are clear power
hierarchal differentials Chin's unable
to engage in spaces where they can
really verbalize what they've
experienced and have those experiences
taken seriously reported and kind of
cascaded up to upwards in terms of being
dealt with do you think what people need
to be perhaps more present and vigilant
of what's happening around it and really
interrogate those spaces because you
know to encounter the violent act in the
first place and interchange it will you
actually end up encountering the double
violence because in
every frame individuals always punish
where it's verbally reputationally or
fiscally or challenging those
inequitable or countering environment I
think you've met some real interesting
things and I've got some relatives as
well who and their NHS you took it's
exactly the same issues and this is not
a initially unique to higher education
this this is playing out consistently
across lots of organizations and Paul
let them and any reflections on that I
think are sort of you know struck by
some that the amount of work that needs
to go in to make sure that people
understand and I educated on on these
issues because for for many why
practitioners in higher education they
don't have to encounter these things on
the daily basis so when when these
things happen or you know it's it's new
it's novel and if they haven't had any
conversations prior to that any
education prior to that in terms of
understanding what the situation look
like looks like and as a active
bystander what can I actually do then
you just end up with those Jason was
saying that kind of either not noticing
or then going up to your toes of the
saying I hope you're okay when actually
you could have done this um don't with
some support in that moment any any sort
of thoughts on there I'm a bit torn I
think for me maybe less so on the sort
of situation the the experiences of
individuals and more so on the
experiences as an institution like one
in an institutional project and
sometimes I'm torn between this idea of
like as an institutional project we have
to change hearts and minds you know and
we have to make sure that everyone
understands everyone's you know got the
knowledge and fully aware of the
experiences of all students and
sometimes I just feel like we just need
to have more accountability in place
right we just need more processes in
place that that make sure that people
don't get away with racist behavior and
I think there are some people that don't
understand but I think
who will understand a lot quicker if
there's some accountability or
repercussions to racist behavior or you
know disk image discriminatory behavior
and I also think the more dangerous
people are those people that do
understand and know that they can get
away with it so I think I am torn and I
think there is a place for training and
professional development and all that
sort of thing but I also I also feel
like sometimes within institutional
projects we hide a lot behind data we
hide a lot behind all the excuses that
people make and we just need processes
it and place them that make people have
to answer to you know why do you have an
awarding gap and what are you trying to
do about it these are sort of direct
questions I think we need to kind of
have answered and keep or learn I think
that's a good place for us to end
obviously this conversation will
continue so please do online engagement
conversation contacts are our panelists
and keep obviously keep talking about
these issues in your institutions I just
like to say thank you to Jason and
Paulette for this part of today's
conversation that's obviously always a
delight to speak to survey to view into
in to hear your views as well and yeah
we found the conversation very very
engaging so thank you so much for taking
time out of your day so what's gonna
happen now is that we're going to take a
15-minute break for you to grab a cup of
tea or a cup of coffee please don't go
anywhere we'll be back at quarter past
so that's 11:15 and we'll have another
panel with two fantastic speakers and
then our final session will be at twelve
so please do come back and join us at
11:15 thank you can I also just add the
epic music is about to start again so
those of you who are enjoying it will be
glad to hear and if you are streaming us
through Facebook we have not managed to
expand the zoom capacity if you wish to
try and go join us again on June 4 1115
you will be very welcome and thank you
again for your patience while we resolve
the issue
you
[Music]
brilliant thank you all this 11:15 which
means we are back and ready to kick off
for our next couple of sessions our next
two sessions so the first one will be on
intersections and capturing and acting
Oh Marilyn can you not hear me Hilary
can you hear me so I can hear you just
let's give let's see whether Marilyn can
Merlin can you hear me now okay so just
suggest that we start with Hilary and
will communicate offline with Marilyn to
just try and sort out the issue
brilliant thank you I'm not having you
[Music]
let's see okay well I
I will I will kick things off I'll
introduce the tea speakers and then I
think one key should be able to get in
touch with Maryland but let me see
whether I can contact Mannion quickly
obviously we're getting is to feel like
I need a piece of paper to hold up to
say yep we'll do that that's that sounds
like a good plan the number website you
know I've never done is it's a resume
call before before March and then on
hundreds and hundreds of these for
getting used to it um but I would say
actually you know to see them we've got
about 900 people joining and you know
this is a really good and effective way
to get in touch with lots of people and
have a conversation like this and
Twitter is very much alive and so please
do keep tweeting please to keep the
conversation there so this section is on
intersections capturing and acting or
lived experience we have two speakers
Marilyn of course and Hillary you can
see and in this section we want to talk
a bit about the characteristics that
shaped the lived experience and
limitations of Baima to category and the
sustainability of some of these projects
to enhance the experience Marilyn can
you hear us
no I don't think she can so we'll hold
on this um but I think speaking first
would be a Hillary to be a Bobby oh who
is the incoming vp h e at the NUS
mastering the students ask one of the
best jobs in higher education has just
finished her term as the undergraduate
education officer Bristow I see and
during her time in that role she does a
lot of work focused on decolonize in the
curriculum creating links with
employability personal development and
alumni for black and babe
students and pushing for a proactive and
transparent approach to tackling racism
she has a degree in social policy and
while a student was chaired the s Youth
widening participation network and a
committee member of the African and
Caribbean Society and just a few days
into a roller and USM she was gonna have
a fantastic term Marilyn can you hear me
no I thought I thought I heard myself
okay but I'll introduce Marilyn I'm a
professor and wholeness is the professor
of Education and engagement and practice
and directed the student engagement
director of student engagement at the
university over Hampton she's the Deputy
Chair tackling of the tackling racism
task force for London hire a leading a
stream of work on the awarding gap her
scholarship is on enhancing teaching
quality and social justice she has
extensive experience on across secondary
schools and AG teaching initial student
teach education student engagement
consultancy and senior leadership and
she has a voice on several education
governing and advisory boards and her
achievements have been recognized and
awarded an OBE for services to teacher
education - we'll wait for my Lancer to
get back on line with us but we'll start
off with Hilary Hilary will speak for a
couple of minutes hopefully by then and
then we'll take some questions so Hilary
over to you great thank you I'm actually
day three into MBA BPHC so I'm still
very new and if I make a mistake don't
hold me to it and so I thought when I
was preparing this introduction it would
be good for me to sort of characterize
and what lived experiences are and what
they look like before talking about what
it really means to listen and to many in
current work and within mhe and I think
firstly and the first point I want to
drill home is that I'm lived experiences
aren't monolithic in nature they are
very diverse and complex and and it's
important that we recognize this when we
are looking and hearing and listening to
and black people and we've lived
experiences of racism I think in
understanding the plurality and the
diversity and using lots of big words
because I'm trying to sound fancy for my
first time speaking so forgive me if
nothing makes sense and but really
understanding the plurality and
diversity of black people we really need
to and
sector step up and and stop trying to
get black people to speak to us if we're
not prepared to give them the space and
the platform and to have their
experiences valued and and really
explored in a way that can talk about
their intersections with their
experience and so I can give an example
as myself I'm a black woman and very
often you'll find in the sector that
you're idle talking about race or you're
talking about gender and never really
together and I think it's important that
we find ways of bringing in those
intersectional conversations especially
with much more minorities and identities
and and I'm thinking especially about
black trans people for example you get
very very little space in this
conversation and and any there um I
think and in doing this we need to
become more open as a sector and and
really and I know you've heard all of
this before but prepared ourselves to be
uncomfortable and I think the key thing
and in doing this is making sure that we
are open to unlearning some things and
then also learning some things that we
didn't expect to learn so and not
looking to sort of take off what you
read in a book but really being open to
hearing new things and and now going
into speaking about Y meter and like
really be conscious about who you're
speaking and speaking to you and we need
to be careful not to box black students
into you sort of comfortable definitions
that are good for our tracking and with
metrics if you saw my own campaign I
talked a lot about this and sadly in a
music video that should never be found
and but nevertheless I think it's
important that we really make sure we
humanize the way we talk to and engage
with black students and black staff
members in this conversation and to
quickly touch on Baima I'm sure Mary
Alice and Mary Lynn is going to talk
more and about it and there's three
reasons why I think we need to think
really really and like really really
hard about you know not using it as much
as we we do right now I think first the
way of homogenizes the experiences of
black people asian people and ethnic
minorities and in a way that it's it
centers it on not to being white and
which inherently centers whiteness as
the norm and takes away from the fact
that you know black experiences aren't
just in relation to whiteness that
they're their experience it's in and of
themselves and we need to recognize that
I think secondly we need to make sure
that we don't use them because it brings
a brief misunderstanding and in our in
our sector in in our society I think we
need to recognize that racism isn't a
homogenous experience nobody experiences
racism the same way and I think really
understanding that you know racism
towards black people anti black racism
and racism it towards Asian people for
example or other minority ethnic groups
are very different in many ways even
though there are shared experiences and
we need to really be acknowledging that
especially in looking at how we are we
are moving forward in tackling racism
and probably to keep this last bit of
this bit short and it doesn't relate to
anybody I mean I couldn't go around
quoting myself Fame and and I'm I'm
Ghanaian like there's not a word in
Ghana
that's called veins and like it's
probably not the best word to use it you
really want to make and this
conversation accessible I think secondly
and now going to talking about how
you're engaging these students and
giving them the spaces to talk I think
right now and I'm sure you've heard this
as well and that we need to do things
differently and be innovative and with
how we do it and I think what's been
really really inspiring for me is that
I've come from a background and working
and studying and that has seen
initiatives put forward to make sure
that you know these conversations are
much more accessible and and I think
what has been key here was making sure
that in in inviting these conversations
we are empowering black students to make
these spaces their own and make it safe
spaces for themselves in a way that
isn't sort of boxed in by what
institutions think and our safe spaces
and and this can really foster a sense
of trust and shared experience community
and validation amongst the black
community and to be free in opening up
and sharing their experiences after blue
bristles on a little bit here and
because and as I was starting my role at
Bristol we had introduced a scheme
called black men black women talk and it
was essentially a scheme I mean a
program that was set up by a student and
to enable black students and to come
together and and speak with one another
and share their experiences in a safe
space for each other
which brings me on to my point so in my
voice right and brings me on to my point
and talking about how are we going to
engage students we need to engage see
that's like cheese to them as partners
and not as test subjects and and giving
that black people have been gaslighted
for centuries and still are today I
think it's important that we give them
back the power and enabling them to
create community insight giving the
confidence and validation and to allow
their voices to be heard and and of
course you all know that this should be
underpinned with the correct support for
trauma and and and support in getting
through the impacts that racism has had
on them my last few bits I'm so in
talking about approaches to solutions
and my head and I live and forgive me
for being blunt and it should never be
expected for black people to come up
with the solutions to their own
oppression it just it doesn't make sense
to to be expected to solve problems that
you did not create for yourself and I
think it's important that real
responsibility is taken in doing this
beyond just and beyond just sort of
making excuses and all sort of excusing
yourself and by feeling like I guess
there's a safe space now that has been
made and people are uncomfortable
talking about race where they don't put
the responsibility on black people and
yet when black people are involved the
responsibility for whether a program or
a scheme passes or fails feels like it's
burdened on them and I think it's
important that we remove that from them
especially for the mental and emotional
impact and it has on them secondly and
when we listen to black people I said
this before but please don't listen to
black people just to tick off some ideas
that you've really made in your rooms
about them and then just sort of like
here for them so like say the key word
that and you want to hear and then sort
of take off your solution that's not how
you do it I think it's really important
that we listen and hear what black
students and staff are actually saying
they need and not just what you want to
do I think finally and we need to
decolonize our approaches this goes back
to my point about it being centered on
whiteness I think it's important that we
don't only push the tackle racism to try
and make black people equal on par with
white people and I think it's important
that we we sort of wipe the slate clean
and allowing empowering and lift black
students and start to be able to
to create their own measures of success
and their own measures of of living in a
way that they throw the most empowered
and safe and in an environment that
embraces welcomes and cares for them and
I believe you want me to bring my
recommendations up now um later and yeah
good for it qu and I'm not sure if I've
gone over I'm quite attractive person so
you're all friends will you meet me in
person and so first of all I think it's
important that as a sector we are
proactive and that means being prepared
to engage with and and that's not only
just like sign up to this event you went
to like this cool one key event and
that's you like your your your purgatory
done and it's it's it's about like
properly engaging with being curious
like asking questions and actually
getting involved in black led
initiatives and I think that also means
opening your versus you probably seen on
Twitter a lot open your classes and and
funding these initiatives and and look
at how you can tangibly provide
resources whether it's free rooms or
through I don't know I'm the income case
if there are so many things you can do
and and on this point I think it's
important that you listen to your
student union officers and because then
a perfect bridge to say getting you know
the solutions on the table and actually
showing UN students watch these awards
will be done and secondly and we need to
expand the colonization work outside of
just EDI teams so easy I serum on your
side and senior management and students
and a middle and lower management staff
and all need to be involved in the
decolonization work because
decolonization in itself is a
transformative process that needs to be
institution wide and and not P smell and
so we need to be really really conscious
that we do that at all levels and of our
institutions and I would recommend that
you you have some sort of external and
advice and support in that to keep you
accountable to the work you're doing so
you're not just doing what's like half
the wall or and just like good enough
and the final thing I want to say is on
on a more sort of a less tangible level
and as a sector we need to be prepared
to be opened up to criticism and and and
being open up to being called out for
racism if it's happening at your
institution which I'm I'm sure I'm sure
and like nobody is nobody's in
and I think what what it needs to be
there's two things it first of all needs
to be humble you need to be humble in in
accepting that these are real
occurrences that are happening and
people have have cooled them out and I
think there needs to be transparency and
acknowledging this and and looking to
actually you know make sense all within
in tackling it and the priority is to
shift away from protecting institutional
representation and move more towards
protecting black students and staff and
whistleblowers for racism and that's a
really really key if you really want to
see meaningful change and at your
institutions and it goes to say that I
think it's also just like it goes beyond
do institutions and and I think there's
a responsibility to sign own itself in
in this work and I really get involved
in in tackling other race related issues
whether it's tackling and the the racial
the racialized elements of prevention
and how prevent has targeted students
and to tackling racial abuses on and off
campus and looking at how policing
affects different students in different
groups in in different ways and I think
it's important that and we recognize
this that's my school intro done I hope
that was okay hearing and my fancy words
worked and thank you yeah fantastic as
always you covered a lot of things and
some really good and clear and practical
steps at the end there so lots to unpack
and Marilyn I'm reliably informed that
you are back with us and you can hear
and I did the introductions
did you introduction Ernie I say but
thank you so much again for taking time
out of your day to contribute to this
conversation and yet over to you you've
got to say okay well thank you all and
apologies for dropping out earlier but I
had technical issues and therefore I
haven't heard you introductions and I
haven't unfortunately heard of all of
Hillary but I do know Hillary I do know
the things that she's been saying and I
did hear that the first half of the
session before the break so I want to
take a moment we need to share some
ideas around the theme of intersections
and around the theme of lived
experiences and from listening to the
first section and the last bit that I
just heard from Hillary I know that a
lot of
points have been covered and some of
them have already been raised so I'm not
going to revisit them in detail now but
what we'll do is we'll unpack them as
part of the conversation so in terms of
intersections we know that they exist
and they me intersections is simply
about where things overlap where things
interconnect and they exist across all
levels of the organization and
universities are no different to that so
amethyst already talked to us and
established that actions need to be
undertaken at the institutional level
and when we talk about the institutional
level we're talking about the work that
happens in departments the work that
happens in faculties and in our schools
the places where all the policies are
made and where policies are implemented
and that's about strategic leadership
that's about management's so there's an
issue around the strategic leadership in
the vision and about the management in
terms of how we implement those are two
pointers that I want to discipline and
then we need to focus on you know where
things are done and things have done in
the teams in professional service in
teams in academic teams in our
classrooms so I want to focus on the
things that we can do at an individual
level a group level for our students in
the everyday work that we do we need to
actually take action to support and to
make interventions for colleagues and
for students at all points of that
learning journey and just as employees
so taking action is going to require a
desire to act so somewhere in here and I
know that Paulette talks about hearts
and minds we need to have a desire to
act a confidence to act it's being need
to have knowledge on how to do it and
bravery in it up to be able to do this
and very much so in terms of being brave
we also have to be looking about them
what that means in terms of the support
mechanisms to be able to give us the
tools that we need to be able to do
these things so we're talking about an
organizational she
the cultural shift and that again as I
said is top-down but I'm going to talk
just a bit more on the bottom up so
organizations are made up of people our
universities are making for people we
know that collectively we protest
against historical structures against
structural racism but it's the
individuals and it's two groups that can
make a difference to things like beim
attainment gaps pain awarding gaps if
each of us as colleagues commit to make
a difference and that can be cumulative
so we talked about the issue of language
and I'm positioning this in terms of
intersectionality so I know that when
talking to colleagues about how they're
going to be involved in and how they
grapple with tackling things like racial
disparity racial equality but they are
really uncomfortable with the words are
not short on what words to use and how
to kind of approach it so we know from a
very pragmatic response that governments
and the Haiti sector needed to use the
term bane and we use it as an
abbreviation is a catch-all it's a tall
to record it's a tall to monitor to
monitor ethnicity to report on
significant equity gaps between the
different ethnic groups and to look at
things like how different groups are
performing in terms of access or non
continuation and assessment and all of
those sort of measures that we're all
aware of but we've already heard that
this term bane comes with a lot of
warnings it's something that we should
use with caution so when we're using it
in a pragmatic and for tools and for
monitoring you know that's fine but
we've got to recognize that it's loaded
with intersections when we talk about
the be in vain we're talking about
political black black African black
Caribbean what exactly do we mean when
we talk about the a in Vaes are we
talking about Asians all Asians South
Asians Chinese Middle Eastern what about
minority ethnic so when we talk about
that minority yes because is that only
people of color that we're talking about
while we talking about gypsies Irish
travelers you know people who would
identify as why but would still fit in
the bane box so when we think about
Baymen we talk about intersectionality
we need to know about how these terms
came to be we need to understand the
shift in language from colored to black
to be a me to bein we need to understand
that historical context we need to
understand the meaning as to how and why
it came to be but more than that what's
really more important is to know about
the lived experiences of the people that
these terms respond to or actually
referred to so if we're going to take
action we need to hear form and have
represented a range of pain voices
across all levels of the organization
it's only when we can get the voices of
all bein groups heard picking up the
life and the lived experiences of all
bein groups that we can start to
influence our policy influence our
decisions and then come up with policies
and decisions that are going to impact
on the people but neither in the ways
that they need it so it kind of goes
without saying that things are not a
homogeneous group and therefore the
whole notion of intersectionality takes
on a whole life of its own when we're
talking about University and we're
talking about how we work with our
students so we know that that beign
group is then sub stratified into sects
and into class and it's an age and it's
agenda and that list can go on you know
disability sexuality but then when we
think about the data that we hold on our
students intersectionality comes in
again their commuter students then
mature students there you know so each
and every time you bring another layer
of intersection into it you have to
think what does it mean for what we do
and how we do things so any solution
that we come up with and that we
identify is going to have to be nuanced
it's gonna have to be adapt
to meet the needs of the student
population the star within the
organizations in which you work in then
there's no one-size-fits-all model or
solution and there is no silver bullet
but what there is it's that in terms of
recommendations they and I'll start to
you know bring those in in terms of we
need to know our students so I think
that one of the recommendations that we
all need to commit to is to know our
students we've got supporting the work
we've got to find out about their lived
experiences
who are they what are their drivers all
of the barriers what are their
aspirations and then we've got to make
sure that our provision and our offer is
meeting those supporting them where they
are now for the future something where
they are now but also to prepare them to
be able to have successful clean futures
and successful lives beyond the
university so we've got to capture that
data alongside the data that we keep in
the university and we've got to use that
data in a smart way so my second
recommendation is about the use of data
we need to have data that's credible but
isn't contested by staff so every time
you give it to them they say are but
it's not this it's class it's not visit
something else they've got to understand
and use the data and use it in a nuanced
way to make sure that they can address
the issues that they face on their
programs in their modules with their
students so that's something else that I
think that we could follow up so another
one of my recommendations and I would be
put in on the table is that you've got
to do the work and Hilary's already said
this it's not something that you look to
the champion in the organisation that
you look to the department person who's
been given this responsibility all that
you look to the bane person amongst your
staff clippin amongst your colleagues
actually every time a student turns up
to a module it's new and they have to
learn and read and do the work in order
to power
well if you want to work with your
students and making sure that you're
putting on an offer and tackling racism
and tackling this issue you've got to do
the work you need to find out and take
on board and you know just look at what
it is you're going to do so you can't
assume anything about lived experiences
lived experiences matter and we've got
to look at identifying from that what
was the actual causes and not just pull
on sort of solutions which are easy and
which touch the sort of symptoms so I'm
going to stop there and open it up to
the conversation Thank You Marilyn them
a lot that you've covered they're trying
to we've been talking about today and so
thank you for that I'm gonna kick off
with a question from me and then over to
Debbie to see whether we've had anything
come through so if any anybody who is
listening please do ask any questions
we've got some time to answer I think
both of you talks on the importance of
engaging their students Hilary you spoke
about the importance of using their safe
spaces in order to give give black
students the the right space and sort of
in the sense opportunity to unpack how
they're feeling about certain issues
before I'm taking them through to
university I just wanted to know whether
you had any kind of examples of good and
here we touched on them Marilyn I know
you will have seen them at your
institution um what are the good
examples of the way in which those
voices have been heard and any kind of
practical examples of the way in which
people have got to know their students
in a level that isn't kind of typical at
the moment and I just sort of add to
that very quickly I think it's important
to recognize that historically
universities have known their shootings
very well because they were from a
certain part of the population only
seven percent the population in
university they're all primarily from a
very similar background so didn't have
to do very much worse get to know them
you get the expansion of her education
and all of a sudden you have you know
black people going to university in
large numbers and the the interviews
haven't caught up with understanding
those experiences in the way that
certainly not proportional to the
expansion or and the diversification of
the sector say maybe Hillary start with
you any kind of practical ways in which
institutions can get to know their
students better yeah I I think and what
me and Marilyn and Toby spoke and I
think what is really interesting is that
and I think they tool is important and I
won't say there is an important I think
it's important to actually know like
know students as people and I went in
where in the world where institutions
are growing so fast and and and the
sector is growing so quickly that it's
becoming so depersonalized to knowing
your students and that often you'll see
students come and go without any
interaction and I think there's a part
in really trying to to convince and and
really try to get to know students in in
terms of people and personal
relationships and I think what's also
been helpful is that the example I gave
about black men and black women talk
that goes on that Bristol and is very is
important because there's an element of
therapy that is nice throughout it and
and and having that sort of community
therapy means that you are able to find
spaces where black students can be
together in a way that isn't draining
but instead it's a it's a space where
they can feel and validating and
empowered and and and filled up with the
confidence and the reassurances that
they get from people of their own
community and and I think in in making
that something that is accessible for
the university to access and I think
it's worked well because it's very non
intrusive in nature and so the person
and the staff member who needs a Bristol
and has done a very good job in terms of
making sure that you know it's still
sort of in control of students so
students actually feel as partners and
with the University in delivering that
and but but it means that that student
can also work with the universities you
pick up on key things at the University
we need to implement and going forward
in in tackling racism and I think going
back to the point I made earlier about
safe spaces and I would I don't
one sort of like safe space that is
perfect and and and as I was thinking
that's when I came to the conclusion or
feeling that safe spaces are any safe
places when you empower people to make
it their own and and and essentially I
think you listen is going to be what's
key and sorry the comments are
distracting me listening is going to be
what's key and in in all of this that
like when you get black students and and
like in Asian and ethnic minority
students together you need to give them
the power and autonomy to make that
space what they need it to be to be able
and to express their shared experiences
and lived experience as well and yeah I
hope that answers that
well yes if Lee Anne Murray any thoughts
on on that question yeah absolutely
I'm former um just one let's say the
classroom perspective if I must ask your
academics to get to know their than the
students it's sometimes it's simple
things and it's really difficult as
you've just described when you've got
large lectures and there's a time in the
model there's no flexibility in the
model to do these things but if possible
and there's a timetabling thing so this
is when it becomes an institutional
response as well but if there's gaps in
there but the rubric in so that there if
you can arrive to the session 5-10
minutes earlier so that people can maybe
and let students know that you're always
there five or ten minutes earlier or if
you've got a you know a two hour or an
hour and a half lecture that you
actually say well in the last fifteen
minutes we're going to have that open to
just kind of pick up any issues where
there's any learning you know when if
you're asking someone to that's one
still question can you just say your
name you know so I'm Marilyn and I want
to ask you so-and-so so that people get
to know names and start to see some of
those little things that you can start
thinking about in terms of you know
managing classroom interactions but more
generally in terms of we work hands with
very much got a model of students
partners and we're trying to ensure that
our student partners are sometimes
rewarded for some of the work that they
do because if they're doing the work
then actually they ought to be paid to
do that work and it's not paid less
leave the actual rate of work
but some sort of reward of
acknowledgment that time is important
and their contributions are important so
but looking at ensuring that students
who involved in things like decision
making in enhancement activities but not
just once which are initiated by the
university but that we do things with
the students and for the students and
help them to come up with things so
concrete examples for us would be things
like we've worked with when we worked on
other tainment gap project my colleague
and and dear friend at Queen Mary's um
doctor as one she works with a small
group of students and we worked with
them as researchers they undertook
research on behalf of the awarding gap
project and what they said was that they
understood what it was like to be in the
classroom they were the ones that were
taking the assessments and if they were
asking staff to very assessment to think
about alternative forms then they would
be prepared to undertake research around
there and be able to say this could work
well have you thought about this why
don't you try that so that's a little
example of partnership working other
examples of things like a glucose
students came to us and said we really
feel that we need some concrete work
around sort of mentoring and coaching to
help students move on and they set up up
here mentoring scheme we worked with
them and supported them and helped to
establish a major is part of the system
but it was a student who initiated it
the students that we sent on the
external training who came back with the
knowledge and then worked with our staff
to help to develop it so we need to
create opportunities for staff and
students to be able to do those things
and those things take these sources they
take time they need to be recognized
they need to be resourced in terms of
they said workloads whether it be time
whether it be funding whether it just be
space so that people can come together
and do these things
they won't happen if it's just an add-on
and it's
just something you do in your own time
and then taking on both the point that
Hillary's already made the emotional
labor that it carries one of the things
that our students fed back to us in our
attainment gap project was that part and
parcel of taking on the responsibility
of doing this and having to talk to
academics who maybe be marking their
work and tell them that some of the
things you're doing they're not nice
some of the things you're doing are not
helpful and we want you to change we
want you to stop and that's a hard
conversation for a young person who's
vested and you know having to work
alongside those colleagues and worried
about the impact it might have on their
that their future attainment but we've
had some real good examples of students
and start setting up liaison groups to
do things like decolonize the curriculum
and people are beginning to look at how
working with students when programs have
been we validated that student panels
are part of that so lots of small things
very nuanced
for the different departments but very
much if the approach is a student as
partners one it's usually important and
that that labor thing is you know it's
not just about you know remuneration
it's one thing as well they need to be
effectively rewarded for that work but
then you know are they being supported
to deal with lots of the issues that
will be coming through in lots of these
lots of cases decisions are sort of the
funnels for other experiences and having
to deal with trauma in a sense for the
first time in this sort of way training
for those students so if you're going to
undertake these activities on behalf of
the organization then to get an
additional accreditation some sort of
recognition of that way and so support
in terms of welfare and well-being
sometimes finances and some time
accreditation so that whole kind of way
of working is part and parcel of some of
the solutions Debbie have you had any
questions yeah I've got a whole range
coming in I was going to pick up this
point I think but I think it's been
really adequately covered about the kind
of I guess impact on students of having
to kind of I guess relive their lived
experience for you know in order to
inform their institution and and the
consequence of that and I think a
related question is one that came
at the very beginning which is a what do
culturally competent student services
look like what would that mean in
practice a great question and I think I
think sometimes very non-traditional
ways and I I think what's really really
what's really stood out to me over the
past month or so is that and in the wake
of the murder of George III remember
like I'm not I I haven't not been
listening very long but you know being a
sabbatical officer that in that time and
be in a black sabbatical officer rather
and the trauma that I felt was
unbelievable and I I don't know if I can
ever tell you and I don't if I can ever
properly characterize how traumatic it
fell and to you know watch that video to
come into workers and have to deal with
issues of race and and talking about how
it's how it's related to my experience
and and and and sort of trying work
through trying to be like professional
and and dealing with that show my at
that at the same time I think in terms
of looking at culturally competent care
right I want to be emphasize my point
about that community and community is
such a big thing that I think is often
underestimated within and the black
community and and and it goes right to
validating people's experiences I think
right now what happened with drilloid
and it was horribly
it was horrible having to watch you know
him dying video but I think I think it
created a bigger point of you know why
does it take us to watch a video of a
man being murdered for us to actually
believe that these experiences are real
and is that what it takes for us to stop
being gaslighted and I think if we're
looking at culturally competent care
it means we're looking at ways of
validating those experiences first and
then we can look at how we're going to
you know really experiences for what
they are and then tackle them I think
right now we're in a space where you
know that institutions are talking about
coaching the competent cares report and
support mechanisms and which quite
frankly I don't know if I've come across
a genuinely robust one in terms of
reporting racism I think as a sector and
we have reporting
complaints and for all sorts of issues
but race is something that has a big gap
in the sector at the moment in being
able to report about and and I think if
we're going to look at that we need to
be able to find a way of like you know
really finding ways a validating those
experiences acknowledging them reporting
them and giving at the actual trauma
support and and well-being support for
black students and to be able to heal
from that and and that's not just a few
counseling sessions that's a whole sort
of course and and a real redemptive and
redemptive action from institutions and
perpetrators and to show that they're
moving forward and trying to push
forward from from these incidences and
promoting the structures that continue
and turn our racism to persist Marilyn I
think this is one for you I mean there's
been some strides in the wider policy
environment and we've heard people
talking in the chat box about the kind
of the incentives on institutions to you
know just you know to take action across
the institution so we've got the race
equality charter we've got access and
participation plans and and and chaff
date so it kind of breaks down you know
differential student outcomes hi how
much of an influence is that is that the
right way to proceed yeah I actually
think that having some formal structures
and building building this whole area
into what we do as our everyday business
and try not to make it something on top
of is going to be one way to make sure
that people participate and see it as
part of their daily work so I think
things like the access and participation
plan is crucial the targets in that plan
should be known and owned by everybody
in the university everybody should know
what it is that the university is
working towards what their gaps are and
how what targets that you know what
action plans are in place to to achieve
those targets I think that the race
equality charter should be mandatory
everybody should do it it should have
teeth
should actually be merged with badged
with a long side the access and
participation plan so the organization's
see the need and I know that a totally
agree I'm very much a people centered
and wanting to talk to real people in
real lives but we can use that data to
also help the situation so for example
at a module level if you know what is
happening with your students so whether
it be their feelings and their responses
to the NSS the test data that you have
but you know what your targets are in
relation to access and participation
plan and you've got real data so for
example you've got a group and you know
for example that that group are students
who maybe came in through one
qualification forum rather than another
students who are predominately living
off campus and community and you know
something about your students you might
then be able to start thinking about one
of the specifics that I need to do so
for example if you want to increase
student outcomes in terms of our being
students and getting you know two ones
and first degrees then you might want to
say well how many Bane students have we
got who are averaging top 50s bottom
suits you know top two two marks and if
we know we've got a bundle of students
who have taught - - how do we get them
over the boundary what is it that they
need are there some specific things that
can be put in for specific group of
students so the data will allow you to
do some of those things but I agree it's
definitely not the answer to everything
so one of the projects that we did at
Roehampton was that we anonymized 5,000
data sets on our students in terms of
ethnicity and what we did was we said
well if we take ethnicity and look at
for example their engagement and
participation and then we add on to it
things like what happens if we keep
ethnicity constant and add on commuting
and then add on whether or not they live
on an off side add on what their
religion is add on their social class
add on all of those kinds of things does
it make a diff
in terms of the students who do well or
not and what we found was even when we
took everything into account all those
intersectionalities there was still a
differential for race and ethnicity and
if that differential still exists then
it's got to be something that we're
doing because we're filtering out all of
those kind of social things and those
things that people say it must be
because the students are poor it must be
because the students live or far away it
must be because they've got caring
responsibilities so if you take all of
that out what's left so the data then
gives you the imperative and that's why
I say clean data credible data that
staff don't have to keep saying oh it's
got to be wrong we don't believe it we
don't trust it's not assets them needs
to be on the table
absolutely Hilary one final one to you
and we've had a question about the role
of the SU in holding institutions
accountable and obviously this is
something that you you're extreme
extremely close to but actually we've
had another question which I think which
is about online platforms and because
obviously our context is that we're
doing everything online right now and
and and it's you know and it's
challenging for us used to you know to
do their work in in that context so and
particularly in the context of what you
were talking about about you know
forging communities and bringing people
together creating those safe spaces is
that is that possible online do yes you
have a role in that and what's the kind
of role of issues and accountability how
generally one minute please that's a
great question and I think first of all
the role of issues in talking about like
calling out racism I think I think it's
less about the role of the SU so I think
issues doing really really effectively I
think it's more about institutions and
how they take that that corner I mean I
think often in institutions get called
out by there s useful racism and it's
met we've been shut down to access to to
senior management some meetings to being
involved in projects and I think it's
teachers need to think really really
hard about you know how prepared are
they like it's in my opinion I think
it's better you get called out by your
Union then you get called out and by
well you know
in a way that will save you a lot more
publicly and in a way that would hurt
you a lot more and so I think I think if
you're not prepared to hear from your
new years and there's something wrong
inside that you really need to tackle -
to really understand what it means to
call out racism and how important it is
that you take that and I think secondly
in talking about building communities
online I think I think it is a challenge
for us but I think it can be done I
think we need to be finally in the
sector we need to do things that are
different and that are that are weird
sometimes I over the past and a few
months I found so many book clubs and I
found so many people starting plant
families I've become a plant mom
recently and now I don't know plants you
know I think there's so many ways you
can get people into communities and
without it feeling so much slomique
enriches it having a purpose for what
you want them to do and what you want
them to achieve and feedback to you and
and so like I guess the quickest thing
for me to say just have fun with it be
fine be innovative just don't don't make
it so prescriptive that is inaccessible
and and you'll do fine Lynn thank you
well constant time and we've had a
fantastic discussion thank you again
Hillary and Marilyn for joining us a
delight as always and I'm sure people
will be in touch to invite you to other
events as well to talk about these
issues but thank you so much for for
taking your time good to see you and now
we move on to our final session of the
day which is about leadership who are
the leaders and what are their
responsibilities and really pleased that
professor Randall Whittaker can join us
today for this last session please do
stick with us for the last half an hour
and professor whisker is pro
vice-chancellor academic at least
College of Art is born in South Africa
and trained as a musician in
conservators in Africa the Netherlands
and the Czech Republic
here's extensive experience as a senior
manager within specialist professional
education and there's a strong interest
in equality diversity and inclusion so
really lucky to have you with your sense
of experience here with us today
um so this such the session is about
leadership as we know there are very few
black and BMI senior leaders in higher
education and that too has a knock-on
effect on the outcomes for staff and
student surrounded Kinte your
reflections on this and and from your
experience as well Thank You Emmett a
and thank you everyone it's always
difficult when you are the last speaker
in an event especially with one with
such eloquent and articulate speakers
before you so many of the key points and
I have address they have covered so I
have to take a slight different approach
to not be too repetitive however I will
start off by saying that University
structures are complex and for the
purpose of this talk I use senior
leadership to refer to those individuals
in powerful decision-making positions so
think about that in the academic sphere
in professional services the executive
and of course governance the lack of
black people at university seen in that
leadership level is lamentable we are
still dehumanized and demonized by the
color of our skin and phrases like a
lack of pipeline is used to explain away
in action it is inexcusable that our
universities have so few people with
lived experience at a senior leadership
level the seemingly unwillingness and
lack of collective accountability to
address this lack of representation
provides the perfect environment for
toxic racism to thrive in the absence of
experienced or lived experience white
leaders they need to reflect on the
privileges they enjoy because they are
white and think through how they can use
their privilege to address systemic
racism in the absence of lived
experience senior leaders white senior
leaders must have empathy for
and show an understanding of the black
lived experience it is not the
responsibility of black people to
educate white people about race white
latest must take individual
responsibility to educate themselves
stop asking black people to do so
conversation about racial injustice is
complex and difficult but essential as a
senior leader you must be forensic in
examining understanding and addressing
the racism within your University view
the claims of tolerance and commitment
to equality diversity and inclusion make
your policies stack up how effective is
your rollin equality diversity and
inclusion training and development
programs how do you measure its impact
what is going wrong in your periodic
review or course approval processes for
your rippln for your curriculum still to
be white do you understand that
advancement advancement or some white
woman is not evidence that your
university or senior leadership team or
governing body is diverse are you
listening to and hearing directly from
black students black staff and black
governors do not make it keep a critical
and superficial statements about
addressing racism read the room as you
will have completely missed the point of
the present moment black people have
heard it all before because our life
experiences have been tinted with racism
as a senior leader you must do the work
make the significant structural changes
required for your university to become
anti-racist you must become actively
anti-racist through your actions anti
racism is not policy it is a set of
values and principles against which to
measure all work a commitment to execute
visible changes addressing race equality
is no longer good enough you must be
accountable for it I would also like to
briefly talk about the acronym be AME
which all the speakers have addressed so
here is my brief take on this
homogenizing be AME is not only lazy but
also problematic who exactly are you
talking about when you use it the AME
has known only ones and it's use impacts
the lives of people of black people
negatively agent is not the same as
black B AME is being used to Gaslight
the black experience and mask in action
as a senior leader you must take
responsibility for challenging and
checking language stop using the AME say
black when you mean black in response to
addressing racism in your university or
if your response to addressing racism in
your university is yet more mandatory
diversity training please stop and
rethink as a senior leader you must
acknowledge the limitation of diversity
and inclusion training programs the
mandatory to our unconscious bias
diversity training program has not made
new University anti-racist you must make
the significant structural changes
required to do so
not making these structural changes
preserves the status quo the racism
remains being aware of racism does not
fix racism now that the momentum of the
black life matters protest and the
social media outrage has been lost will
you he's speaking out against racism
will you still be an ally
you can do better keep the conversation
going as a senior leader you must not be
silent or defensive about racism do not
get involved involved in the well
washing of racism be sincere be honest
being transparent about where you are
and where you need to be is a strength
not a weakness now it's a time for
university sealing leaders to use their
platform to take meaningful action
against racism
thank you anything thankee randall a lot
to unpack there and real interested in
particularly the consi had to say about
the homogenize a ssin of the experience
there's some stuff that we can turn back
around unconscious bias training and and
diversity training as he highlighted and
the first so I had a question about what
you mentioned right at the beginning
about that pipeline typically and I'm
sure others on this school will know
this pipeline better than me but you
know you do your undergrad master's PhD
junior research tip you then you might
be made an internal role in the
department head of school head of school
PVC PVC then you know you get on to the
senior team and then vice chancellor and
I'm sure their loss of other ways of
doing that
look what we are today the Vice
Chancellors from today would have done
that but started back years and years
and years ago at a time when they said
to look very very different so and III
understand what you said in terms of
people looking at that and going well
there are no people coming through the
system so it's understandable that it's
that what thoughts do you have about
actually completely sort of in a sense
turn that up and saying well if that
pipelines are not going to be produce us
with the diverse talent that we need
we're gonna have to find another way of
doing it or we're gonna have to
two circuits that traditional model
because even if we were to start fixing
the first part of the pipeline today
we're not gonna see that until 56 years
time so so what are your thoughts are on
kind of as in essence short cutting that
pipeline to make sure we get the most
talented senior teams I mean I think the
first thing to say Amity is from my
perspective that talent is there it
exists it's about how you get to those
individuals so let's talk about
University governance and appointment
panels in terms of senior posts and how
that typically works in our university
sector that there will be a appointment
panel made up of a selection of your
board perhaps a few students and from
the su included but typically
universities in the UK Commission
executive search companies to undertake
this work executive search companies in
the UK in terms of their work with
universities in particular sign up to a
voluntary code of conduct so there are
very few of them Minerva is one good
example that is absolutely open and
transparent about their data how many
applications from black individual how
many have made it to the long list
how many have made it to the shortlist
how many appointed that lack of
transparency within the other executive
search firms is the real problem because
you cannot see what is happening through
all those various stages how many people
actually make it through through the
long list from application so there's an
inherent bias and that I've been vocal
about this before I find it lamentable
that as universities we should be using
agencies that sign up to a voluntary
code of conduct
so governing bodies are risk averse
quite rightly so risk averse people are
easily led to make safe decisions I'm
not saying that isn't universal
case but we have got to ask the question
that within the amount of universities
we have in this country wide diverse etc
and I mean diverse in sense of
curriculum that why are we in a
situation that there are so few black
people in senior leadership positions
that start with looking at how you can
duck your appointing and recruitment
authors particular stuff
that's a really that's a really
important point because there is our
distinction then obviously between
the sort of internal approach internal
appointments for positions which are a
bit sort of lower down on the food chain
as it were but but actually ever point
about when senior leaders are appointed
the executive search companies are sort
and their support is sought for and then
you know what are they doing that the
lack of transparency about that process
and and often targeting existing pools
that they may have and similar similar
forceful governor's appointments as well
external agencies are used and how
diverse are they and has that
conversation being had about with them
about about this agenda I think is
important yes I do think I would say
there are questions for the regulator to
ask themselves here as as well what are
they doing about this particular
situation so we have this bars
regulation and across all aspects of the
work of universities but when it comes
to making senior appointments that you
know to use your phrase that have
capabilities and then to use blacks
phrase that can understand the urgency
of the situation
they're very silent I'm not asking for a
condition of registration but I'm asking
and pleading to someone for someone to
listen why our universities allowed to
use executive search companies that sign
up to a voluntary code of conduct it's
not acceptable cuz it really it's a
really important point um Debbie I
wondered whether we have any questions
coming through at all
absolutely I think there's there's a
basket of questions about training and
runs oh you said you were selfish you
were quite clear about the kind of
issues with with delivering lots of
training to kind of raise awareness and
actually I would say you mentioned
earlier that you feel that there's quite
a important distinction to be made away
from unconscious bias and towards racial
equity but I think there's also
throughout throughout the chatter it's
been clear that - you know to some
extent the problem is whiteness it's
white privilege it's a lack of
understanding among white people or lack
of confidence sometimes about we where
weirder what our real is and what we
should be doing and an ability to
recognize this and and and an ability to
take action and while I'm really
conscious that you know I shouldn't
present this to you as question for you
to solve you know but there's quite you
know if if training has its three
serious limitations could you comment on
that further but also you know are there
things that white people can be doing to
be better ourselves yes I think I'd be
quite emphatic but I'm not here but I
mean I can see some of the chants
popping up and you know it isn't about
the right kind of training and who does
it
specialist training by specialists
people with experience is can be more
effective but as senior leaders and as
individuals we have got to recognize the
limitation you know because often we sit
doing it online or sit in a seminar room
have someone talk with you for for two
hours maybe less and then the idea is
that you use that knowledge and apply it
well actually sometimes you don't have
the ability to apply and then crucially
very few institutions measure the impact
because they don't know how to measure
the impact of the training and I'm not
quite sure I mean I think I come
probably from the school of thought that
says you can't train unconscious bias
you know trained bias out of people you
need to learn how to live with it I
understand the people bet that's not how
with someone asking well what does
effective training look like I think
some of the best examples of effective
training and in terms of equality and
diversity and if you want to include
bias in that please please do or those
LED but people with lived experiences
giving some of the participant engaging
at the training the opportunity to
engage at that level to year how it
manifests itself in in lots of different
ways so if I do not have the question to
this I know in my own institution I look
very carefully at what that program
looks like what we can do better who can
deliver it I'll be using the right
people are we measuring it you know
these programs are a huge investment for
many universities I don't have the
answers to that I'm highlighting that as
senior leaders we should realize the
limitations and we need to we need to do
better thank you
I would say do you want to pick up on
that question about bias versus equity
yes and then this comes from my own
experience actually of doing some really
training when I was in US and it's the
first time I've been engaged in a
process and obviously split out so my
staff and white staff had had different
sessions but I think coming coming down
it comes down to as Randall said having
somebody with the experience and being
able to hear those experiences and the
ways in which they manifest themselves
how it made the individuals feel acts
and and that sense particularly the
university context and how it made them
feel in terms of them being part of the
university community and he can't do
that through a sort of through a sort of
survey or online kind of form sort of
unconscious bias training sometimes just
sort of tells you that you have biases
and then doesn't really tell you what to
do about it whereas actually this is
about understanding and getting a
greater insight on experiences
reflecting them on your own behaviors
and then ideally hopefully making you
more aware and in tune to the way in
which your behaviors may influence
others so that you can then you can then
change and as Paulette said earlier
that's all the only thing you do if an
individual goes through that process and
it completely ignores it there needs to
be sanctions if that behavior continues
and you have robust processes as well
but it's far more than just you know it
and any other things as well is that
individuals are from different stuff
different levels of their education and
understanding so you need somebody with
expertise understands how to but
potentially in a better word a mixed
ability group how we could how you can
sort of educate people in a sensitive
way when you know people will say things
which are offensive and make mistakes
how do you get them by the end of the
sessions to understand just briefly say
that I think there is also evidence that
suggests if you make it voluntary
unconscious bias training for example
those people who are really serious
about it will step forward so you have a
more attentive group to work with and
there you can then become influencers
for it I think it's the mandatory
position that I have issues with because
you know it can be used as a tick tick
box exercise hundred percent of staff at
university access undertaken mandatory
unconscious bike training therefore we
are non racist
we are anti right as well absolute
nonsense you know it doesn't work like
that yes any other questions Debbie yeah
we've been having some questions I guess
people people who are not in formal
positions of leadership and people who
have less power and I think we're
talking about both white and black
people here
people of color who want to kind of
influence want to try to make a
difference want to be a leader in their
own context should we say but there's
not an obvious route to being part of
the decision-making conversation are
there things that those people can be
doing gosh very an absolute excellent
question and I might say to members who
have during this webinar that it's not
easy you know I have to recognize my
privilege to be one of a very few senior
university leaders from the background
that I am in it has been really
difficult to get there and actually it
is it has taken me a long time to be as
emphatic as I am now it is about
confidence it's about using your
platform to address the right things I
also did not join the Academy to be a
token representative for advancing black
leadership in universities no actually I
joined it as a musician believe it or
not but I think there are ways in which
structures can help staff in those
position to feel that they can challenge
that they can question I think a really
important point it's by acknowledging
that we don't all have get it right all
the time and that is fine you know we
will make mistakes conversations about
race are difficult and actually at most
times probably awkward as well so the
worst thing you can do is to not have
them but some of the previous speakers
have given some excellent tips about
what to look for how you can go about
asking asking questions I think you know
there has to be a confidence in asking
the question there has to be a sense
that you're feeling listened to you know
even now I question how much I get
listened to but I'm certainly not silent
anymore but it has taken me a long time
to get there
surely as you sort of touched on that
the challenges with so few it's it's I
doubt there's some sort of network even
though you sort of three or four people
across the sector's you know I often
feel when I enter a boardroom or a
conference in the old normal we used to
have and I also think oh goodness I'm
gonna have to be the only person again
that asks the question about that
diverse senior leadership because there
is no one else in the room but actually
I might wanted to ask question about
something else I do owe it to colleagues
from black backgrounds and students with
black runs black backgrounds to see that
there are people a few but there are
people who are comfortable to raise
these questions and yet he said not
wanting to be kind of typecast as the
person who's going to talk about race so
that nobody else has to yeah tell you
have any other questions some questions
about resourcing here and I think
there's a sort of layer to this which is
about government and and obviously the
Chancellor is making his big speech this
morning and we're expecting some of the
you know the purse strings to be
loosened and but also at the
institutional level you know how I try
to convince senior leaders to make the
resource available and it's something
that's been a theme throughout the event
it's quite interesting isn't it and
someone asks the question I think I'm in
person or in the chat or you might have
even been Marilyn actually addressing it
the race across the charter versus
Athena Swan for example and just very
quickly from me Athena Swan was
excellent
in terms of providing opportunity for
white middle class women part of the
impetus to take it really seriously from
University it is was that in some
aspects of it was linked to aspects of
funding so we have got to be clear
about that so there is an impetus when
there's another pot of money available
for something a pot of money isn't the
answer to this you know if we're going
to see change each university leader and
its governing body needs to make those
structural changes no imbalance of
throwing additional money from the
public purse is going to improve it
because you need the individuals to act
to do it Paris in action
there's excuses these things we're
talking about today we've been talking
about for a very very long time
use your budgeting processes in a
different way commit some of those money
you spend somewhere else on something
like this show your students so you show
your son how important it is to you word
even beyond
the statements work beyond the media
statements the press releases the social
media releases take action but be
accountable for it yourself you do not
get to meet government to tell you how
to do this it's an excuse well I think
that's a very very good place for us to
wrap up today that real call for action
not waiting for the government to tell
us what to do and certainly not wait for
the government to tell us to put in
place regulations which don't quite work
for us actually it's taking the
initiative it's a lesson certainly for
today randall thank you so much for
taking the time to speak with us today
i'm really really interested to hear
your views for your experience on this
thank you to all our speakers as well
for engaging in today's debate thank you
to one key as well from me
personally for allowing a platform for
these conversations to be had this is
certainly want the biggest online events
in higher education on this topic that
I've ever seen so this really really
encouraging it obviously thank you to
everybody who imagine is working from
home thank you to all of you for
engaging please to keep the conversation
going please so you keep thinking about
reflecting on how you can take action
and please keep the conversation going
online social media in the work
and elsewhere so I think that is all for
me but I hope you all have a good rest
of the day and thank you all and thank
you so much MIT for hosting an
absolutely brilliant event once once
they get up and running Thank You rounds
or for your absolutely inspiring
comments and thank you to all of you for
everything you've contributed in the
chat I've been knitting done everything
you've said and make and I'm going to
try and bring it all together and share
those resources as we as we promised the
recording and the slides will be
available after the event and if somehow
you this is your first encounter with
wonky then do do stay in touch with us
sign up to our Monday briefing which is
free read our website and if you are a
member at a subscribing institution you
can get our daily briefing as well we
will keep the conversation going and
have a wonderful day thank you again and
let's let's make the change thanks
you
[Music]